Up to this point, I've only been using the center camera
これまでは 中央のカメラの 画像を 使ってきましたが
image, but now it might be helpful to use side camera
ここで サイドのカメラの画像も トレーニングに
images for training, too.
含めてみましょう
Using the side camera images carries two benefits.
サイドカメラの画像を 使うことには 2つ メリットが あります
One, it's simply more data.
1つは データ量の増加です
In fact, it's three times as much data.
実に その量は 3倍になります
The other benefit is that using these images
これらの画像を使う もう1つの メリットは
will help teach the network how to steer back to the center
車両が 横に それ始めたときに どのように中央に戻るかを
if the vehicle starts drifting off to the side.
ネットワークに 教えられることです
Let's look at the left image.
左の画像を 見てみましょう
This image is a little off to the left side of the road,
この画像は 道路の中央から 少し左に それていますが
but it's paired with a steering measurement of zero.
ステアリング測定値は 0になっています
That's because when this image was taken,
なぜなら この画像が 撮影された時点で
the center of the vehicle really was in the center of the road.
車両の中央が 道路の中央に 位置していたからです
So how do I use this image?
では この画像は どう使えばよいでしょうか
Basically, I want to train the network
私としては ネットワークに対し
to steer a little harder to the right
このような画像を見たら ハンドルを
whenever the network sees an image like this.
右に切るよう トレーニングしたいと 考えています
I'll do this by taking the actual steering
そこで 実際のステアリング測定値 つまり
measurement, which in this case is zero,
0に わずかな修正係数を
and adding a small correction factor to it.
加えます
I could actually draw out a model
本当なら モデルを作成し
and use trigonometry and physics to calculate
三角法と 物理法則に 従って 最適な修正係数を
an optimal correction factor, but I'm just
求めることも できますが ちょっと
going to be lazy and try a correction factor of 0.2.
なまけて 0.2という値で 試してみます
Similarly, for the right camera image,
右側のカメラ画像についても 同様に
I'm going to train the network to steer a little harder
ハンドルを もう少し左に切るよう
to the left.
トレーニングしたいと 思います
I'll do that by subtracting the correction factor
そのために 右のカメラの画像を 使うたびに
from the actual steering measurement
実際の ステアリング測定値から
whenever I use a right camera image.
修正係数が 引かれるようにします
I implement this by looping through the first three
手順としては CSVファイルの 各行で 最初の3つの
tokens of each line in the CSV file,
トークンを ループさせて それを
and I use these to load each camera image into the images
使って 各カメラ画像を 画像配列に
array.
ロードします
Then I add three measurements to the measurements array
次に 3つの 測定値を 今 追加した画像に 対応する
corresponding to each image I just added.
測定値配列に 追加します
Now I should have three times as much data,
これで データの量が 3倍になり
and my model should perform better.
モデルの性能も 向上するはずです
Let's see.
見てみましょう
It looks like the model is indeed
どうやら モデルは 本当に
training on three times as many camera images.
3倍量の カメラ画像で トレーニングしているようです
I'm excited to see how well this drives.
どんな運転になるか 楽しみです
Ooh, it looks like it drives worse.
おっと 運転は ひどくなりましたね
It's just pulling to the left.
左に 大きく それています